Guide to the Emma B. Lommasson Papers 1918-2013
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Emma B. Lommasson Papers
1918-2013
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 934
Lommasson, Emma B. 1911-2019
2.3 linear feet
This collection contains materials documenting the life and work of Emma Lommasson, an employee and alumna of the University of Montana in Missoula. The collection includes photographs, scrapbooks, papers, and ephemera from across Lommasson's 107 years.
Biographical Note
Emma Bravo was born on December 10, 1911 to her Italian parents, Filomena and Giovanni. Her first language was Italian, and her grade school years were spent mastering the English language. In 1929, she graduated from Centerville High School in Sand Coulee, Montana, as valedictorian of her class. Following high school, she enrolled at the University of Montana where she majored in mathematics. She graduated in 1933 and returned to Sand Coulee where she taught mathematics, Latin, and Spanish at her former high school.
In 1937, Emma Bravo returned to the University of Montana and worked as a personal secretary to Dr. N.J. Lennes. She was also working towards her Masters in mathematics, which she graduated with in 1939. Emma married Tom Lommasson in 1939 and helped raise his son, Tom. The Lommassons were married for 30 years; Tom Lommasson died in December of 1969.
By the start of World War II, Lommasson was an instructor in the University of Montana Mathematics Department. She taught in a program designed to prepare young men for service in the Air Force, teaching courses such as Navigation, Civil Air Regulation, and Airplane Identification. Following the war, the University of Montana selected Lommasson as the Veterans Advisor and the Assistant Registrar. She served for 17 years as advisor for the University’s Air Force ROTC Angel Flight, and also became the University’s Registrar and the Associate Director of Admissions and Records. In 2001, the building housing the university’s administrative offices was renamed the Emma B. Lommasson Center in her honor.
Emma Lommasson passed away on November 30, 2019 at the age of 107.
This collection contains materials from Emma Lommasson’s education, employment at the University of Montana, and post-retirement activities. These materials reflect her various roles and positions at the university and her dedication to its students, including through her many awards. The collection also includes photographs of the University of Montana's Angel Flight students.
This collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Personal, 1927-2000, 1.7 linear feet
Series II: Photographs, 1918-2013, 0.2 linear feet
Series III: Ephemera, Circa 1960s-2001, 0.2 linear feet
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The materials in this collection were held by Emma Lommasson until her death.
The materials in this collection were donated to Archives and Special Collections by J. Martin Burke, trustee for the Emma Lommasson Trust, in 2020.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Lommasson, Emma B., 1911-2019--Archives
University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.: 1965-1994)--Employees; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.: 1965-1994)--Students--Photographs; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps; aUnited States. Air Force ROTC.
Universities and colleges--Montana--Missoula; Mathematics--Study and teaching--Montana--Missoula; Aeronautics--Study and teaching--Montana--Missoula; Air pilots--Training of--Montana--Missoula
Colleges and Universities; Missoula
College registrars--Montana--Missoula; Women college teachers--Montana--Missoula
- Personal, 1927-2000; Series I; 1.7 linear feet
  This series includes a scrapbook documenting Lommasson's early educational achievements, documents relating to her time as a student and teacher at the University of Montana, materials and awards from her time volunteering with the University. Also included are scrapbooks for the Montana Fidelis Alpha Chapter of Alpha Delta Kappa for which Lommasson served in leadership roles, including as historian.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Education Scrapbook, 1927-1933; Scrapbook contains clippings and materials marking Lommasson's educational achievements in high school and college (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - High School Diploma, 1929 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Class of 1929 Autograph Book (Box-folder 6 / 1)
  - Montana State University Sentinel Year Book, 1933; Yearbook from Emma Lommasson's senior year in college. Contains many images of Emma Lommasson in clubs and academic sororities. (Box-folder 6 / 2)
  - Commencement, 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Certificate to Teach, 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Undergraduate Degree, 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Centerville High School Yearbook, 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - University Ephemera, 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Master's Commencement and Degree, 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Master's Thesis, 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Air Force, 1962 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Air Force ROTC and Angel Flight, 1962-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Alpha Delta Kappa, 1971-1996 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Award Presentation Speeches and Communication, 1977-1979; Contains Speeches and Press Releases for the Pantzer Award and Career Service Award (Box-folder 6 / 3)
  - Distinguished Alumnus Award, 1977 (Box OS 4)
  - Career Service Award, 1977 (Box OS 4)
  - "Remembering N.J. Lennes," Speech by Emma Lommasson, 1978 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Robert T. Pantzer Presidential Humanitarian Award, 1979; This award is given annually to a person from the University of Montana or the State of Montana who has contributed substantially to making the University a more open and humane learning environment. (Box OS 4)
  - Alpha Delta Kappa, Montana Fidelis Alpha Chapter Scrapbook, 1980-1990 (Box OS 5)
  - Volunteer Award, 1987 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Alpha Delta Kappa, Montana Fidelis Alpha Chapter Scrapbook, 1990-2000 (Box OS 5)
  - Lommasson Center and Bench, 2001, 2012; Contains Photographs and programs for the ceremony renaming of the Lommasson Center and articles about the Emma Lommasson Bench (Box-folder 6 / 4)
  - Emma Lommasson Day Proclamation, December 2, 2011; Proclamation making December 10, 2011 Emma Lommasson Day (Box-folder 6 / 5)
  - "Remembering Emma" Memorial Service Program, December 17, 2019 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
- Photographs, 1918-2013; Series II; 0.2 linear feet
  This series includes photographs ranging in date from Lommasson’s childhood through to her retirement from the University of Montana. The series includes photographs of Angel Flight students. Angel Flight was a women's drill team auxiliary of the Air Force Reserved Officer Training Corps.
  - Emma Lommasson Photographs, 1918-circa 1990s (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Emma Lommasson Photographs, Circa 1920s-1930s (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Emma Lommasson University of Montana, circa 1930s; "She lived at Lennes House- on lawn and outside of house" "Emma Outside North (now Brantley Hall) as a student" (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Photograph Book, circa early 1930s; Photograph book given to Emma by her roommate (unknown) (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Wedding Photograph of Emma Lommasson, 1939 (Box OS 4 /)
  - Airmen Training, 1942; "Emma teaching aviation" (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Family Photographs, 1953; "Emma and her sisters and her mother" "Mother, Father, and Nephew James" (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Angel Flight, Circa 1960s (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Angel Flight and ROTC, Circa 1960s (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Angel Flight and ROTC, Circa 1960s-1970s (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Angel Flight, Circa 1960s-1970s (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Angel Flight, Circa 1960s-1970s (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - "Individual Angel Pictures", 1965-1966 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - "Dress Modeling", 1966; "Emma Modeled for Dress Shop/ Mrs. King" (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - Photograph of Emma, 1973 (Box OS 4 /)
  - Alpha Delta Kappa, 1991 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - Retirement, 1993; 2003; 2013; "Emma outside home at Sand Coulee, MT- the home she grew up in." (Box-folder 2 / 15)
- Emphemera, Circa 1960s-2001; Series III; 0.2 linear feet
  This series contains ephemera from Lommasson's involvement in Angel Flight, her time spent volunteering at the University in multiple organizations, and from the event renaming what is now called the Lommasson Center at the University of Montana.
  - Angel Flight Medal, Circa 1960s (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Distinguished Alumni Award Pin, 1977 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
  - Lommasson Center T-shirt, 2001 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Alpha Delta Kappa Pin, undated (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Academic Fraternity Pins, No Date; Pins for Phi Kappa Phi, Alpha Delta Kappa, and Phi Mu Epsilon (Box-folder 3 / 5)